=Faithful= (Adapted from the novel "Faithful")
= مثير = (معدلة من الرواية "مثير")
=Episode 24, Chapter 12, Part 2= (Justice comes)
= الحلقة 24، الفصل 12، الجزء 2 = (يأتي العدالة)
I'm sorry.
أنا آسف
I couldn't help today.
لم أستطع المساعدة اليوم
It is not your fault.
إنه ليس خطأك
We know about Wu Lian's ability
نحن نعرف عن قدرة وو ليان
to distort the truth.
لتشويه الحقيقة
Without you today,
بدون منكم اليوم
Mr. Lou would have already left here.
كان السيد لو قد غادر هنا بالفعل
And we wouldn't have the chance to retry the case.
ولن تتاح لنا الفرصة لإعادة تجربة القضية
We don't blame you.
نحن لا نلوم عليك
At least half of the people hearing the case
على الأقل نصف الناس من سماعهم القضية
have already believed what you said in the end.
قد ؤمن بالفعل ما قلته في النهاية
They were all cursing Wu Lian.
كانوا جميعا يشنون وو ليان
Exactly.
بالضبط
Wu Lian was not sent to prison today,
وو ليان لم يرسل إلى السجن اليوم
but his reputation in Huaizhou Prefecture
ولكن سمعته في مقاطعة هواتشو
has been ruined.
تم تدميره
Wu An is a rat fink.
وو آن فنغ فطر
He tricked me.
لقد خدعني
I don't think he changed his mind on the spot.
لا أعتقد غيّر رأيه على الفور
When he promised you,
عندما وعدت لك
he was probably already prepared
ربما كان مستعدا بالفعل
to go back on his word at this trial.
عد عن كلمته في هذه المحاكمة
I really underestimated this loyal dog.
لقد قللت حقا من شأن هذا الكلب المخلص
Wu Lian had the upper hand today,
كان لدى وو ليان اليد العليا اليوم
but it's not the end yet.
لكنها ليست النهاية بعد
We still have a chance.
لا تزال لدينا فرصة
Madam.
سيدتي
A trial was held today.
أجريت محاكمة اليوم
It's about the Rulan Case seven years ago.
إنه يتعلق بقضية ران قبل سبع سنوات
Wu Lian was not convicted.
وو ليان لم يتم إدانته
(Ning Mansion)
(قصر نينغ)
What's the current situation
ما هي الحالة الراهنة
with Wu Lian's case?
مع قضية وو ليان؟
It got big.
كان كبيرا
The Yamen has been crowded these days.
اليامين مكتظون هذه الأيام
But there is still no progress.
ولكن لا يوجد أي تقدم
Mr. Lou also has no way.
والسيد لو لا يمكن أيضًا
Lou Mingzhang can decide
لو مينغتشانغ يمكنه اتخاذ القرار
on this case by himself.
في هذه الحالة بنفسه
Madam.
سيدتي
People from the palace.
الناس من القصر
Imperial palace?
القصر الإمبراطوري؟
It's Mr. Wang, who serves Her Majesty.
إنه السيد وانغ، الذي يخدم صاحبة الجلالة
A decree for Mrs. Ning.
مرسوم للسيدة نينغ
(Goodliness) A decree from Her Majesty.
(الأخلاق) مرسوم من صاحبة الجلالة
I have heard about the case of Wu Lian.
لقد سمعت عن قضية وو ليان
Mrs. Ning was deceived
لقد خدعت السيدة نينغ
by Wu Lian,
من قبل وو ليان
but you've corrected your mistake
لكنك صححت خطأك
and informed me of the truth in time.
وأبلغتني بالحقيقة في الوقت المناسب
So, I will exonerate you.
لذلك، سأبرئك
Mrs. Ning,
السيدة نينغ
you must act cautiously and refrain from repeating past mistakes.
و يجب أن تتصرف بحذر من تكرار أخطاء الماضي
Accept the decree.
اقبلوا المرسوم
Mrs. Ning, accept the decree.
السيدة نينغ، اقبل المرسوم
I accept the decree.
أقبل المرسوم
Greeting, Mrs. Ning.
تحياتي يا سيدة نينغ
Mr. Wang, you must be tired.
السيد وانغ، يجب أن تكون متعبا
I have prepared tea and snacks for you.
لقد أعددت الشاي والوجبات الخفيفة لك
Thank you.
شكرا لك
Please.
من فضلك
How did Her Majesty know about this?
كيف عرفت صاحبة الجلالة عن هذا؟
I really underestimated Meng Wan.
لقد قللت من شأن منغ وان
How did she manage to do it?
كيف تمكنت من القيام بذلك؟
Perhaps I'm a part
ربما أنا جزء
of her plan.
من خطتها
Remember
تذكر
who sent me the Her Majesty's gift?
من أرسل لي هدية صاحبة الجلالة؟
Madam.
سيدتي
The birthday gift from Huangji Embroidery House
هدية عيد الميلاد من بيت هوانغجي للتطريز
has been delivered.
تم تسليمها
Bring it.
أحضره
Yes.
نعم
Greeting, Mrs. Ning.
تحية يا سيدة نينغ
It's you.
إنه أنت
When did you start to work for the Huangji Embroidery House?
متى بدأت العمل لبيت التطريز هوانغجي؟
I know you may not want to see me.
أعلم أنك قد لا ترغب في رؤيتي
But I had no choice.
لكنني لم يكن لديّ خيار
Please forgive me.
أرجوك سامحني
I know why you are here.
أعرف لماذا أنت هنا
You and Wu Lian fight in a trial.
أنت ووو ليان في محاكمة
It's causing a stir in Huaizhou.
انها تسبب ضجة في هواتشو
I do not intend to get involved.
لا أنوي التدخل
You're worried that if Wu Lian is found guilty,
أنت قلق أنه إذا تم إدانة وو ليان
it will implicate you.
سوف تورطكم
Wu Lian is nothing to me.
وو لان ليس شيئا لي
He has no power
لا يملك سلطة
to take me down.
لإسقاطي
To protect himself,
لحماية نفسه
he will do everything he can to take you down.
سوف يفعل كل ما في وسعه لإنزالك
If I were you,
إذا كنت مكانك
I might take the initiative.
قد آخذ المبادرة
If you expose his crimes to the officials,
إذا فضحت جرائمه إلى المسؤولين
you might be exonerated.
قد يتم تبرئتك
What makes you think
ما الذي يجعلك
you can win this lawsuit?
يمكنك الفوز في هذه القضية؟
There is always justice in this world.
هناك دائما العدالة في هذا العالم
Well,
إذن
I seem to have overestimated you.
يبدو أنني بالغت في تقديرك
You are not a smart person.
أنت لست امرأةً ذكية
You may go.
يمكنك الذهاب
Wu Lian.
وو ليان
He's completely useless now.
إنه عديم الفائدة الآن
Don't you have Huai Embroidery now?
أليس لديك هواي إمبراطور الآن؟
No one knows
لا أحد يعرف
how far it can go.
إلى أي مدى يمكن أن يذهب
Good.
جيد
So,
لذلك
I will have fewer problems to worry about.
سيكون لدي مشاكل أقل للقلق
I got the news from the capital.
تلقيت الأخبار من العاصمة
Her Majesty is quite satisfied with Huai Embroidery.
جلالة الملكة راضية تماما مع هواي التطريز
You mean...
هل تقصد...
A new embroidery house is rising.
منزل جديد للتطريز في ارتفاع
An imperial edict from His Majesty.
مرسوم إمبراطوري من جلالة الإمبراطور
(Justice) When I heard about the case of Wu Lian,
(العدل) عندما سمعت عن قضية وو ليان
I was furious.
كنت غاضبة
I order the inquisitor Lou Mingzhang
أنا أطلب المحقق لو مينغتشانغ
to handle the case.
للتعامل مع القضية
This case must be strictly tried
يجب محاكمة هذه القضية بدقة
to seek justice for the innocent.
لتحقيق العدالة للأبرياء
Do it according to the decree.
افعلي ذلك وفقا للمرسوم
Yes, I will.
نعم، سأفعل
I see the light in your room.
أرى الضوء في غرفتك
So I guess you're still up.
لذلك أعتقد أنك ما زلت استيقظًا
The case has not been settled.
القضية لم تمت تسويتها
I can't sleep.
لا أستطيع النوم
You've never mentioned the wound
لم تذكر الجرح قط
on your shoulder.
على كتفك
I'm eager to forget it.
أنا حريص على نسيانه
How can I mention it?
كيف يمكنني ذكره؟
Thank you for coming
شكرا لك على حضورك
to help me.
لمساعدتي
Please have a seat.
يرجى الجلوس
Li Chunfeng's was right.
كان لي تشون فنغ على حق
I have been deceiving myself over the past seven years.
لقد كنت أخداع نفسي على مدى السنوات السبع الماضية
I hide behind the name of Jueming,
أختبئ وراء اسم جيمينغ
unwilling to admit that I am Tian Xiaoling.
غير راغبة في الاعتراف أنني تيان شياولينغ
I thought, in that way,
اعتقدت بهذه الطريقة
I could let go what happened
يمكنني التخلي عما حدث
to Tian Xiaoling.
إلى تيان شياولينغ
But I didn't even have the courage to face it.
لكنني لم يكن لدي الشجاعة حتى لمواجهة الأمر
How can I say I've let it go?
كيف يمكنني القول إنني تركت الأمر وشأنه؟
Many things are easier said
القول الكثير من الأمور أسهل
than done.
مما تم
It's already not easy for you
ليس من السهل عليك
to think this way now.
للتفكير بهذه الطريقة الآن
If I could have understood it earlier,
إذا كان بإمكاني فهم ذلك في وقت سابق
maybe he wouldn't have died.
ربما ما كان ليموت
Between these two things,
بين هذين الأشياء
there are no causal relationships.
لا توجد علاقة سببية
Why would it be blamed on you?
لماذا يتم لومي عليك؟
I once asked Master Huichen
سألت السيد هويشن مرة
why she hadn't shaved your head in the past seven years.
لماذا لم تقسم رأسك في السنوات السبع الماضية
Master Huichen told me
قال لي السيد هويشن
my worldly entanglements were not over,
مشاعري العالمية لم تنته
and the knots were unloosed.
والعشاء لم تُكشف
What are the knots holding you?
ما الذي تمسك بك العشاء؟
Naturally, it's Wu Lian.
بالطبع، هو وو ليان
It's you.
إنه أنت
I don't understand.
أنا لا أفهم
About the incident that year,
حول حادثة ذلك العام
are you blaming Wu Lian or yourself?
هل تلوم وو ليان أم نفسك؟
Master Huichen said
السيد هويشن قال
she understood it all
إنها فهمت كل شيء
when she read your letter.
عندما قرأت رسالتك
You seemed to resent Wu Lian,
بدا أنك تستاء من وو ليان
but in reality, you took all the blame upon yourself.
ولكن في الواقع، أخذت كل اللوم على نفسك
You hid in the Qingshui Nunnery
اختبأت في نزل تشينغشوي
and cultivated yourself.
وزرعت نفسك
It's not only an escape but also a self-punishment.
إنه ليس مجرد هرب بل أيضا عقوبة ذاتية
Just now, you felt guilty
للتو، شعرت بالذنب
for Li Chunfeng's death.
على وفاة لي تشونغنغ
Though you already have the courage to face the past,
على الرغم من أن لديك بالفعل الشجاعة لمواجهة الماضي
if you can't overcome this hurdle,
إذا لم تتمكني من التغلب على هذه العقبة
you will only suffer more.
سوف تعاني أكثر
Seven years ago,
قبل سبع سنوات
Lin Rulan accused Wu Lian.
واتهم لين رلان وو ليان
People said she was slanderous.
قال الناس إنها مشوهة
I've met her.
لقد التقيت بها
I knew she was telling the truth.
عرفت أنها كانت تقول الحقيقة
But when I saw her,
لكن عندما رأيتها
she was already determined to die.
كانت مصممة على الموت بالفعل
I pitied her,
أشفقت عليها
but I didn't sympathize with her.
لكنني لم أتعاطف معها
My father is a private tutor.
والدي معلم خاص
I read more books
قرأت المزيد من الكتب
than other girls,
من فتيات أخريات
so I thought I was different from them.
لذلك اعتقدت أنني كنت مختلفة عنهم
Though what Lin Rulan said was true,
على الرغم من أن ما قاله لين رولان كان صحيحا
it was none of my business.
لم يكن ذلك من عملي
I didn't care.
لم أكن أهتم
She trusted people too easily,
كانت تثق بالناس بسهولة شديدة
so she had this misfortune.
لذلك واجهت هذه المصائب
I thought I was smarter than others.
ظننت أنني أكثر ذكاء من الآخرين
I wouldn't let the same thing happen to me.
لن أسمح بحدوث نفس الشيء بالنسبة إليّ
I deserved it.
أنا أستحق ذلك
Do you know that Li Chunfeng once stole a name list
هل تعرف أن لي تشونغنغ سرقت ذات مرة قائمة أسماء
from the Yanyu Tower?
من برج يانيو؟
He never mentioned it to me.
لم يذكر ذلك لي أبدا
Every girl on that list is
كل فتاة على تلك القائمة هي
just like you and me.
مثلي ومثلك تماما
They all have been hurt by Wu Lian.
لقد أصيبوا جميعا بأذى من قبل وو ليان
Have you ever felt that they brought this upon themselves?
هل شعرت في أي وقت أنهم أحضروا هذا على أنفسهم؟
No, I haven't.
لا، لم أفعل
Why do you think you are different from them?
لماذا تعتقد أنت مختلف عنهم؟
Maybe some of them, just like you,
ربما بعضهم، مثلك تمامًا
always feel that they have done something wrong
يشعرون دائمًا أنهم اقترفوا خطأ
to deserve this.
لتستحق هذا
Wu Lian is to blame.
وو ليان هو المسؤول عن ذلك
They did nothing wrong.
لم يرتكبوا أي خطأ
See, haven't you already figured it out?
أرأيت؟ ألم تكتشف ذلك بالفعل؟
But you are completely unaware of it.
لكنك غير مدركة لذلك إطلاقًا
Have a good sleep.
نامي جيدًا
The day will dawn.
سيفجر اليوم
I received anonymous letters
تلقيت رسائل مجهولة
from the people of Huaizhou.
من شعب هواتشو
The content was appalling.
كان المحتوى مروعا
(Huaizhou) (The letters contain)
(هواتشو) (تتضمن الرسائل)
(personal stories written by those women victimized by Wu Lian,)
(قصص شخصية مكتوبة من قبل هؤلاء النساء من قبل أولئك النساء اللاتي وقعن ضحية وو ليان
(or written by the victim's families.)
(أو مكتوب من أسر الضحية)
(Many local people came to the Yamen to petition,)
(جاء العديد من الناس المحليين إلى يامين لتقديم الالتماس)
(hoping to retry the case.)
(على أمل إعادة محاكمة القضية)
Madame Xu.
السيدة شو
I received the verbal order from His Majesty.
تلقيت الأمر اللفظي من جلالة الإمبراطور
Are you behind this?
هل أنت وراء هذا؟
Since he managed to get an official position
بما أنه تمكن من للحصول على منصب رسمي
through the Zhang family,
من خلال عائلة تشانغ
I have made a back-up plan.
لقد وضعت خطة احتياطية
You use Mrs. Ning
أنت تستخدم السيدة نينغ
to present this letter to Her Majesty.
لتقديم هذه الرسالة إلى صاحبة الجلالة
What if Her Majesty is infuriated?
ماذا لو كانت صاحبة الجلالة مغضبة؟
I cannot allow Wu Lian to have a chance to escape.
لا أستطيع السماح للوو ليان أن تتاح له الفرصة للهروب
If Her Majesty puts the blame on you,
إذا قامت صاحبة الجلالة بإلقاء اللوم عليك
you can deny it all.
يمكنك إنكار كل شيء
I will bear all the consequences.
سأتحمل كل العواقب
I don't like to hear you say this.
لا أحب أن أسمعك تقول هذا
If I was concerned about my safety,
إذا كنت قلقة بشأن سلامتي
I would have stayed away from you guys.
كنت سأبقى بعيدا عنكم
I'm worried
أنا قلق
if Her Majesty wants to save Wu Lian
إذا كانت صاحبة الجلالة تريد إنقاذ وو ليان
to save the face of the court.
لحفظ وجه المحكمة
If it really happens, what will you do?
إذا حدث ذلك حقا، ماذا ستفعل؟
This is just a gamble.
هذا مجرد مقامرة
The outcome is uncertain.
النتيجة غير مؤكدة
Please accompany me to the Yanyu Tower.
يرجى مرافقتي إلى برج يانيو
There
سيكون هناك
will be more witnesses.
سيكون المزيد من الشهود
Are they crazy?
هل هم مجنون؟
Those letters were anonymous.
كانت هذه الرسائل مجهولة الهوية
We really can't stop it.
لا يمكننا حقا وقف ذلك
They exposed those personal affairs
لقد عرّضوا تلك الشؤون الشخصية
to the public for their judgment.
للجمهور من أجل حكمهم
They have no sense of shame.
لا يشعرون بالعار
Master.
معلمي
What's it?
ما الأمر؟
Mr. Lou has arrived with many officials.
لقد وصل السيد لو مع العديد من المسؤولين
They're in the front yard,
إنهم في الفناء الأمامي
calling in maids for questioning.
اتصلوا بالخادمات للاستجواب
I have their servitude contracts.
لدي عقود الاستعباد الخاصة بهم
They should know what to say
يجب أن يعرفوا ما يقولون
and what not to say.
وماذا لا تقولوا
He's just an inquisitor.
إنه مجرد محقق
I'll meet him now.
سألتقي به الآن
(Yanyu Tower) All of you recount
(برج يانيو) كلكم تعيد عد
what was seen and heard here
ما رأى وسمع هنا
over the past years.
على مدى السنوات الماضية
If any of you withhold any information, I'll consider it as complicity.
إذا امتنع أي منكم عن تقديم أي معلومات سأعتبره تواطؤا
Mr. Lou.
السيد لو
I've been working here for over a decade.
لقد كنت أعمل هنا لأكثر من عقد
I'd like to say something.
أود أن أقول شيئا
Too many girls have been hurt
الكثير من الفتيات قد أصبن
in this place.
في هذا المكان
It's awful.
هذا فظيع
I am in charge of cleaning.
أنا مسؤول عن التنظيف
I've seen Mr. Wu more than once
لقد رأيت السيد وو أكثر من مرة
going to the embroideresses' rooms
الذهاب إلى غرف التطريز
alone at night.
بمفرده في الليل
And me.
وأنا
Every time Master went to a lady's room,
في كل مرة ذهب المعلم إلى غرفة امرأة
the next day, it was always my responsibility
في اليوم التالي كانت دائما مسؤوليتي
to change her bedsheet.
لتغيير صحيفة سريرها
Do you remember how many times it happened?
هل تتذكر كم مرة حدث ذلك؟
Too many times. I couldn't remember.
مرات عديدة، لم أستطع أن أتذكر
When Ding Ru had an accident,
عندما تعرض دينغ رو إلى حادث
I passed through the backyard.
مررت عبر الفناء الخلفي
I saw Master and Ding Ru standing
رأيت المعلم ودنغ رو واقفا
by the well in the backyard.
بئر في الفناء الخلفي
They had an argument.
تشاجرت معهم
Afterwards, she jumped into the well.
بعد ذلك، قفزت في البئر
Who is Ling'er?
من هو لينغر؟
Master let Ling'er go
المعلم ترك لينغ ير
seven years ago.
قبل سبع سنوات
It was Ling'er
كان لينغ
who testified
من شهد
that Rulan repeatedly
أن ران مرارا وتكرارا
visited Wu Lian's study at night,
زار دراسة وو ليان في الليل
deliberately seducing Wu Lian.
أغوى وو ليان عمدا
She is just a maidservant.
إنها مجرد خادمة
A maidservant has to do what she is told.
يجب على الخادمة أن تفعل ما يقال لها
Yes.
نعم
Mr. Wu.
السيد وو
I'm afraid you'll have to go to the Yamen again.
أعتقد أنه سيكون عليك الذهاب إلى اليامين مرة أخرى
Take him away.
خذه بعيدا
You don't need to.
لا داعي لذلك
I'll go with you.
سأذهب معك
(Yanyu Tower)
(برج يانيو)
Thank you all.
شكرا لكم جميعا
Over these years,
على مدى هذه السنوات
I've been watching him do evil things.
كنت أشاهده وهو يفعل أشياء شريرة
I have a granddaughter.
لدي حفيدة
Wu Lian has our indentures.
وو ليان لديه ذكاءنا
That's why we betrayed our conscience
لهذا السبب خاننا ضميرنا
and keep silent about the truth.
لزم الصمت بشأن الحقيقة
- Today, we finally spoke the truth. - Yes.
- اليوم، تحدثنا عن الحقيقة أخيرا - نعم
And thank you for giving our indentures back.
وشكرا لك على العودة إلى الوطن
If you want to thank someone,
إذا كنت ترغب في توجيه الشكر لشخص ما
you should thank Ms. Zhang.
يجب أن تشكر السيدة تشانغ
Ms. Zhang?
السيدة تشانغ؟
Do you mean Mrs. Wu?
هل تقصد السيدة وو؟
Yes.
نعم
She gave me your indentures.
أعطتني مظهرك
What do you all plan to do in the future?
ماذا تخطط جميعا للقيام به في المستقبل؟
I want to return to my hometown.
أريد العودة إلى مسقط رأسي
I've saved some money over the years.
لقد وفرت بعض المال على مر السنين
I might start a small business.
قد أبدأ عملا صغيرا
I don't know anyone here,
لا أعرف أحدًا هنا
so I don't know where to go.
لذا لا أعرف إلى أين أذهب
If anyone has nowhere to go,
إذا لم يكن لدى أي شخص مكان ليذهب إليه
you can go to Huangji Embroidery House.
يمكنك الذهاب إلى بيت التطريز هوانغجي
They will offer you jobs.
سوف يعرضوننا على وظائف
- Thank you.
- شكرًا لك
Great!
رائع!
(Yanyu Tower)
(برج يان يو)
Which one of you is Mr. Wu Lian?
أي واحد منكم السيد وو ليان؟
That's me.
هذا أنا
Here are your appointment letter and seal.
ها هي رسالة التعيين الخاصة بك المختم
Thank you.
شكرا لك
I need to return to the capital.
أحتاج إلى العودة إلى العاصمة
So I will take my leave.
لذلك سأغادر الآن
See you.
أراك لاحقا
Mr. Lou.
السيد لو
As you know,
كما تعلمون
any officials who commit a crime
أي مسؤولين يرتكبون جريمة
must be sent to the capital for trial.
يجب إرسالهم إلى العاصمة للمحاكمة
In this way,
بهذه الطريقة
I'm afraid you can't handle this case here.
أنا خائف أنه لا يمكنك التعامل مع هذه الحالة هنا
Whether or not I can handle it,
سواء كان بإمكاني التعامل مع الأمر أم لا
it is not for you to decide.
ليس لك أن تقرر
Take him away.
خذه بعيدا
- You... - Go.
- أنت... - اذهب
(Three days later) (Huaizhou Prefecture Yamen)
(بعد ثلاثة أيام) (مقاطعة هواتشو يامن)
All the women present are witnesses.
جميع النساء الحاضرات شاهدات
(Benevolence)
(الولاء)
Wu Lian, do you plead guilty?
وو ليان، هل تقر بالذنب؟
I'm innocent.
أنا بريء
Both witnesses and physical evidence are present.
كلا الشهود و الأدلة المادية موجودة
You have no choice but to admit.
لا خيار لكم سوى الاعتراف
Even if Wu Lian is found guilty,
حتى لو وجد وو ليان مذنبا
the sentence is just three years in prison.
الحكم فقط ثلاث سنوات في السجن
If he accepts corporal punishment instead,
إذا قبل بدلاً من ذلك
after that, he will be able to leave.
بعد ذلك، سيكون قادرا على المغادرة
- Isn't it too lenient for him? - Yes.
- أليس متساهلا جدا له؟ - نعم
Those young ladies
هؤلاء السيدات الشابات
were all harmed by him.
تضرروا جميعا منه
You can't let him get away with this.
لا يمكنك السماح له بالإبتعاد عن هذا
- Yes, don't let him off.
- أجل، لا تدعه وشأنه - أجل، لا تدعه يخرج
Here's the verdict.
هنا هو الحكم
Wu Lian raped women,
وو ليان اغتصب النساء
smuggling embroidered goods, bribing officials,
تهريب سلع مطرزة ورشو المسؤولين
and killing Li Chunfeng.
وقتل لي تشون فنغ
The evidence is conclusive and charges established.
الأدلة قاطعة وتم إثبات التهم
According to the law, he is sentenced to the punishment of flogging
ووفقا للقانون، حُكم عليه بعقوبة الجلد
and exiled to the northwest for three thousand miles,
ونفي إلى الشمال الغربي لمدة ثلاثة آلاف ميل
never to be pardoned in his lifetime.
لا يمكن العفو عنه أبدا في حياته
Great!
رائع!
Lou Mingzhang.
لو مينغتشانغ
You ignore the law and seek personal revenge.
أنت تتجاهل القانون وتسعى إلى الانتقام الشخصي
I'll report you to the Censorship Bureau.
سأبلغ عنك إلى مكتب الرقابة
I received His Majesty's decree.
تلقيت مرسوم جلالة الإمبراطور
This case has a profound impact, with unforgivable crimes.
لهذه القضية أثر عميق بجرائم لا تغتفر
A heavy sentence should be rendered.
يجب إصدار حكم ثقيل
- Good.
- جيد
- Great, a just ruling.
- رائع، حكم عادل
- Awesome.
- رائعة - رائع
Men Wan.
من وان
Take him away.
خذه بعيدا
Lou Mingzhang.
لو مينغتشانغ
Lou Mingzhang, I'll kill you.
لو مينغتشانغ، سأقتلك
(Benevolence)
(الإحسان)
♪The wind is blowing♪
♪ الرياح تهب ♪
♪Snow is falling♪
♪ الثلج يهبط ♪
♪I'm fearless♪
♪ أنا بلا خوف ♪
♪I'm determined♪
♪ أنا عازم ♪
♪And move on♪
♪ ويتحرك ♪
♪Move on in any case♪
♪ انتقل في أي حال ♪
♪I follow my passions♪
♪ أتابع مشاعري ♪
♪Looking back♪
♪ نظرة إلى الوراء ♪
♪I bring back a flood of memories♪
♪ إنني أعيد فيضان من الذكريات ♪
♪I've been♪
♪ لقد كنت ♪
♪Through a lot♪
♪ عن طريق الكثير ♪
♪It is unforgettable♪
♪ إنه لا يُنسى ♪
♪May the sky be clear♪
♪ يرجى أن تكون السماء واضحة ♪
(Justice) ♪Dawn arrives♪
(العدالة) ♪ الفتى يصل ♪
Carry out the punishment.
ينفذ العقوبة
Yes.
نعم
(Retribution is inescapable.)
(العقاب أمر لا مفر منه)
(Today,)
(اليوم،)
(we finally took revenge for those victimized women.)
(أخيرا، انتقم لأولئك النساء الضحايا)
(Their families and friends)
(عائلاتهم وأصدقائهم)
(can finally unleash their anger and grievances.)
(يمكن أخيرا إطلاق العنان لغضبهم والمظالم
(The blood debt is finally paid in blood.)
(دين الدم أخيرا) يتم سداد أخيرا بالدم
(More importantly,)
(الأهم من ذلك،)
(it's a warning)
(إنه تحذير)
(for evildoers and schemers.)
(للمهربين والمخططين)
(Whether they are highly positioned)
(ما إذا كانوا في مكانة عالية)
(or highly intellectual,)
(أو فكرية للغاية)
(and whether or not they're nobodies,)
(وسواء كانوا منتمين أم لا،)
(those doing all kinds of evil will eventually face justice.)
(أولئك الذين يرتكبون كل أنواع الشر) سوف يواجهون العدالة في نهاية المطاف
(Those who harbor vain hope will ultimately be caught.)
(أولئك الذين لديهم أمل بلا جدوى سوف يتم القبض عليهم في نهاية المطاف)
(Karma has a way of finding them.)
(كارما لديها طريقة العثور عليهم)
(Huaizhou Prefecture Yamen)
(مقاطعة هواتشو يامن)
This is the last lantern.
هذه هي الفانوس الأخير
(An adult girl is fearless.)
(الفتاة البالغة لا خوف)
What are your future plans?
ما هي خططك المستقبلية؟
I will return
سأعود
to my old life.
إلى حياتي القديمة
With the help of Mrs. Ning,
بمساعدة السيدة نينغ
the embroideress hiding in your place
المطرقة المختبئة في منزلك
have their local identities.
لديهم هوياتهم المحلية
Thank you.
شكرا لك
What about you?
ماذا عنك؟
Returning to Qingshui Nunnery?
العودة إلى مقاطعة تشينغشوي؟
No.
لا
Master Huichen was right.
كان السيد هويشن على حق
I've been stuck in the past.
لقد كنت عالقا في الماضي
I do nothing wrong,
لا شيء خاطئ
but I have imprisoned myself for seven years.
لكنني سجن نفسي لمدة سبع سنوات
I'm too silly.
أنا سخيفة جدًا
In the future, I will live well.
في المستقبل، سأعيش حياة جيدة
I think this is what he wants.
أعتقد أن هذا هو ما يريد
I'm glad to hear that.
يسعدني أن أسمع ذلك
What about you?
ماذا عنك؟
Do you really never return to the Xu family?
ألا ستعود حقا إلى عائلة شو؟
I only hope
آمل فقط
he will have a happy life.
أن يتمتع بحياة سعيدة
As for me,
أما أنا
I promised Rulan back then
وعدت رواندا في ذلك الوقت
to accompany her
لمرافقها
to see the splendid views in this world.
لرؤية الآراء الرائعة في هذا العالم
I'll settle down in a beautiful place
سأاستقر في مكان جميل
with a small yard and a swing,
مع فناء صغير وأجيال
living a peaceful life.
أن نعيش حياة سلمية
Now, it's time to realize it.
الآن، حان الوقت لإدراك الأمر
Won't it be hard to meet again?
ألن يكون من الصعب الاجتماع مجددًا؟
If it's meant to be, we'll meet again.
أن نلتقي مجددًا إن كان مُقدرًا لذلك
(Wait in the boudoir for seven years, but nothing is forgotten.)
(انتظري في الخزانة لمدة سبع سنوات لكن لا شيء منسي
(Give a treasure hairpin to the hero. Ignite a candle light.)
(أعطه دبوس شعر كنز للبطل) أشعل ضوء شمعة
(The wilderness also has emotions.)
(البراري لديه مشاعر أيضا)
(Troubled by worldly affairs, seeking tranquility in the mountains.)
(تمسه الشؤون العالمية) بالسعي إلى الهدوء في الجبال)
(Pray to Silkworm Mother at the door. Worship the God of Wealth inside.)
(أراي أن تطمئن على الباب) عبدِ إله الثروة في الداخل
(The young man goes with the wind and returns in time.)
(الشاب يذهب مع الرياح وتعود في الوقت المناسب)
Let's drink it up.
دعنا نشربه
To Sanniang.
إلى سانيانغ
To Chunfeng.
إلى تشون فنغ
To Rulan.
إلى رولان
Fortunately, the officials are wise.
لحسن الحظ، المسؤولون حكمون
This time,
هذه المرة
Wu Lian can never recover from this.
وو ليان لا يمكن أبدا أن يتعافى من هذا
She saved my life years ago.
لقد أنقذت حياتي قبل سنوات
Now,
الآن
I finally have a chance
لدي أخيرا فرصة
to repay her.
لرد لها الجميل
My leg doesn't get limp for nothing.
ساقي لا يعرجن مقابل لا شيء
Now,
الآن
I have finally done justice to Miss Lin.
لقد اعترف أخيرا بالآنسة لين
(An adult girl is fearless.)
(الفتاة البالغة بلا خوف)
(Chen Zhiyuan, the prefect of Huaizhou Prefecture,)
(تشن زيوان حاكم مقاطعة هواتشو
(as the local county governor,)
(كحاكم محلي للمقاطعة،)
(you're incompetent in handling cases and neglects your duties.)
(أنت غير كفء في معالجة القضايا) و تهمل واجباتك)
(Such misconduct is inexcusable.)
(هذا سوء السلوك لا يغتفر)
(Now, you're demoted to the magistrate of Qingyuan County.)
(الآن، تم تخفيض وزنك إلى القاضي من مقاطعة تشينغيوان
(You shall depart for your new office immediately.)
(يجب أن تغادري إلى مكتبك الجديد على الفور)
Mr. Chen.
السيد تشن
It is getting late. Let's go.
الوقت متأخر، دعنا نذهب
(Huaizhou)
(هواتشو)
You are here to laugh at me.
أنت هنا لتسخر مني
I am here to say goodbye.
أنا هنا لأقول وداعًا
I haven't lost yet.
لم أخسر بعد
Does it hurt?
هل هذا مؤلم؟
Those women felt more pain than you do now.
شعرت أولئك النساء بالألم أكثر مما تشعرين به الآن
You always compare the women to fallen plum blossoms.
أنت دائما تقارن النساء لهبوط أزهار البرقوق
Now you have lost everything,
الآن لقد فقدت كل شيء
including the hands you value the most.
بما في ذلك يداك الأكثر قيمة
Now,
الآن
are you not a fallen plum blossom?
ألم تسقط زهر البرقوق؟
Wu Lian.
وو ليان
Have you ever regretted it even slightly?
هل سبق لك أن أعربت عن أسفها لذلك حتى قليلا؟
Lian.
ليان
Lady Wu.
السيدة وو
You have grown up.
لقد كبرت
How have you been?
كيف حالك؟
They all say I'm wrong.
كلهم يقولون إنني مخطئ
Lian.
ليان
Don't embroider plum blossoms anymore.
لا تتطرّق إلى أزهار البرقوق بعد الآن
Put down the needle.
ضعي الإبرة
Lady Wu.
السيدة وو
Wu Lian swallowed a needle!
ابتعد وو ليان عن إبرة!
- Hurry.
- بسرعة
Hurry!
بسرعة!
(Huai'an Prison)
(سجن هواي آن)
(Tomb of Lin Rulan)
(قبر لين ران)
I owed you a favor when I went to your pharmacy
كنت مدينة لك معروفا عندما ذهبت إلى صيدليتك
to buy medicine back then.
لشراء الدواء آنذاك
Today, I finally paid it back.
اليوم، دفعت ثمنه أخيرا
You can rest in peace now.
يمكنك أن ترتاح في سلام الآن
♪Withered orchids are falling♪
♪ أوركيد مطر تنهار ♪
♪In a misty rain♪
♪ في مطر رهيب ♪
♪I've been traveling♪
♪ لقد كنت مسافرين ♪
♪Across the country♪
♪ عبر البلاد ♪
♪I'm as sad as you♪
♪ أنا حزينة بنفس القدر ♪
♪Walking through high-rises♪
♪ المرور عبر الارتفاعات العالية ♪
♪Sobbing desperately into my hands♪
♪ تمسكا بيدي بشدة ♪
♪The candle is on♪
♪ الشمعة في الجوار ♪
♪Even if I can't return♪
حتى لو لم أستطع العودة ♪
♪I have no regrets♪
♪ ليس لدي أي ندم ♪
♪The wind is blowing♪
♪ الرياح تهب ♪
♪Snow is falling♪
♪ الثلج يهبط ♪
♪I'm fearless♪
♪ أنا بلا خوف ♪
♪I'm determined♪
♪ أنا عازم ♪
♪And move on♪
♪ ويتحرك ♪
♪Move on in any case♪
♪ انتقل في أي حال ♪
♪I follow my passions♪
♪ أتابع مشاعري ♪
♪Looking back♪
♪ نظرة إلى الوراء ♪
♪I bring back a flood of memories♪
♪ إنني أعيد فيضان من الذكريات ♪
♪I've been♪
♪ لقد كنت ♪
♪Through a lot♪
♪ عن طريق الكثير ♪
♪It is unforgettable♪
♪ إنه لا يُنسى ♪
♪May the sky be clear♪
♪ يرجى أن تكون السماء واضحة ♪
♪Dawn arrives♪
♪ الفتى يصل ♪
(Wait in the boudoir for seven years, but nothing is forgotten.)
(انتظري في الحديقة لمدة سبع سنوات) لكن لا شيء منسي
(Give a treasure hairpin to the hero. Ignite a candle light.)
(أعطه دبوس شعر كنز للبطل) أشعل ضوء شمعة
(Mr. Lou insisted on restoring me to my official position.)
(أصرّ السيد لو على إعادته إلى منصبي الرسمي) إلى منصبي الرسمي
(But I can't do this job anymore.)
(لكنني لا أستطيع القيام بهذا العمل بعد الآن)
(The young man goes with the wind and returns in time.)
(الشاب يذهب مع الرياح ويعود في الوقت المناسب)
(The Imperial Guard Bureau has urged me.)
(مكتب الحرس الإمبراطوري) حثني
(I should return to the capital to face punishment,)
(يجب أن أعود إلى العاصمة) إلى العاصمة لمواجهة العقوبة
(looking for opportunities to make up for past mistakes.)
(يبحث عن الفرص) للتعويض عن أخطاء الماضي
(The wilderness also has emotions.)
(البراري لديه مشاعر أيضا)
(There's too much work to do in the Huashi Convoy.)
(هناك الكثير من العمل المطلوب القيام به في قافلة هواشي)
(Well,)
(حسنا،)
(I'm going to be busy.)
(سأكون مشغول)
(Pray to Silkworm Mother at the door. Worship the God of Wealth inside.)
(من الرذاذ إلى الدودة الغينية) أمي عند الباب اعبد إله الثروة في الداخل)
(Many ladies have ordered Huai Embroidery.)
(العديد من السيدات أمرت هواي التطريز)
(I'm going to hire more people.)
(سأوظف المزيد من الناس)
(Troubled by worldly affairs, seeking tranquility in the mountains.)
(تأثّرت بالشؤون العالمية الساعين إلى الهدوء في الجبال)
(It's been seven years.)
(مر سبعة أعوام)
(I should go home.)
(يجب أن أذهب إلى المنزل)
(Everyone,)
(الجميع،)
(Let's part ways here.)
(دعنا نمر هنا)
(Maybe I'll see you around.)
(ربما سأراك في الجوار)
♪The wind is blowing♪
♪ الرياح تهب ♪
♪Snow is falling♪
♪ الثلج يهبط ♪
♪I'm fearless♪
♪ أنا بلا خوف ♪
♪I'm determined♪
♪ أنا مصمم ♪
(If one only thinks for one person,)
(إذا كان المرء يفكر فقط في شخص واحد)
(it's not a kindness.)
(إنه ليس لطف)
(A single lantern)
(فانوس واحد)
(creates limited light,)
(يوجد ضوء محدود،)
(but so what?)
(ولكن ماذا في ذلك؟)
(As long as this lantern remains luminous,)
(طالما أن هذه الفانوس شديدة الانفجار لا تزال مضيعة
(it can light more lanterns,)
(يمكنه إضاءة المزيد من الفوانيس)
(leading to a million lights.)
(تؤدي إلى مليون ضوء)
(As bright as the rising sun,)
(ساطعة مثل الشمس الصاعدة،)
(it can illuminate the long night.)
(يمكن أن تضيء الليل الطويل)
(The End)
(النهاية)
♪Withered orchids are falling♪
♪ أوركيد مكة تنهار ♪
♪In a misty rain♪
♪ في مطر رهيب ♪
♪I've been traveling♪
♪ لقد كنت مسافرين ♪
♪Across the country♪
♪ عبر البلاد ♪
♪I'm as sad as you♪
♪ أنا حزينة بنفس القدر ♪
♪Walking through high-rises♪
♪ المرور عبر الارتفاعات العالية ♪
♪Sobbing desperately into my hands♪
♪ تمسكا بيدي بشدة ♪
♪The candle is on♪
♪ الشمعة في الجوار ♪
♪Even if I can't return♪
حتى لو لم أستطع العودة ♪
♪I have no regrets♪
♪ ليس لدي أي ندم ♪
♪The wind is blowing♪
♪ الرياح تهب ♪
♪Snow is falling♪
♪ الثلج يهبط ♪
♪I'm fearless♪
♪ أنا بلا خوف ♪
♪And move on in any case♪
♪ وتواصل العمل في أي حال ♪
♪I follow my passions♪
♪ أتابع عواطفي ♪
♪Looking back♪
♪ نظرة إلى الوراء ♪
♪I bring back a flood of memories♪
♪ إنني أعيد فيضان من الذكريات ♪
♪I've been through a lot♪
♪ لقد مررت بالكثير ♪
♪It is unforgettable♪
♪ إنه لا يُنسى ♪
♪Dawn arrives♪
♪ وصل الغضب ♪
♪Walking through high-rises♪
♪ المرور عبر الارتفاعات العالية ♪
♪Sobbing desperately into my hands♪
♪ تمسكا بيدي بشدة ♪
♪The candle is on♪
♪ الشمعة في الجوار ♪
♪Even if I can't return♪
حتى لو لم أستطع العودة ♪
♪I have no regrets♪
♪ ليس لدي أي ندم ♪
♪The wind is blowing♪
♪ الرياح تهب ♪
♪Snow is falling♪
♪ الثلج يهبط ♪
♪I'm fearless♪
♪ أنا بلا خوف ♪
♪And move on in any case♪
♪ وتواصل العمل في أي حال ♪
♪I follow my passions♪
♪ أتابع عواطفي ♪
♪Looking back♪
♪ نظرة إلى الوراء ♪
♪I bring back a flood of memories♪
♪ إنني أعيد فيضان من الذكريات ♪
♪I've been through a lot♪
♪ لقد مررت بالكثير ♪
♪It is unforgettable♪
♪ إنه لا يُنسى ♪
♪Dawn arrives♪
♪ وصولها ♪